Cache Invalidation

“There are only two hard things in Computer Science: cache invalidation and naming things.” – Phil Karlton

Once a URL is cached by a gateway cache, the cache will not ask the application for that content anymore. This allows the cache to provide fast responses and reduces the load on your application. However, you risk delivering outdated content. A way out of this dilemma is to use long cache lifetimes, but to actively notify the gateway cache when content changes. Reverse proxies usually provide a channel to receive such notifications, typically through special HTTP requests.

Caution

While cache invalidation is powerful, avoid it when possible. If you fail to invalidate something, outdated caches will be served for a potentially long time. Instead, use short cache lifetimes or use the validation model, and adjust your controllers to perform efficient validation checks as explained in Optimizing your Code with Validation.

Furthermore, since invalidation is a topic specific to each type of reverse proxy, using this concept will tie you to a specific reverse proxy or need additional efforts to support different proxies.

Sometimes, however, you need that extra performance you can get when explicitly invalidating. For invalidation, your application needs to detect when content changes and tell the cache to remove the URLs which contain that data from its cache.

Tip

If you want to use cache invalidation, have a look at the FOSHttpCacheBundle [https://foshttpcachebundle.readthedocs.org/]. This bundle provides services to help with various cache invalidation concepts and also documents the configuration for a couple of common caching proxies.

If one content corresponds to one URL, the PURGE model works well. You send a request to the cache proxy with the HTTP method PURGE (using the word “PURGE” is a convention, technically this can be any string) instead of GET and make the cache proxy detect this and remove the data from the cache instead of going to the application to get a response.

Here is how you can configure the Symfony reverse proxy (See HTTP Cache) to support the PURGE HTTP method:

// src/CacheKernel.php
namespace App;

use Symfony\Bundle\FrameworkBundle\HttpCache\HttpCache;
use Symfony\Component\HttpFoundation\Request;
use Symfony\Component\HttpFoundation\Response;
// ...

class CacheKernel extends HttpCache
{
    protected function invalidate(Request $request, $catch = false)
    {
        if ('PURGE' !== $request->getMethod()) {
            return parent::invalidate($request, $catch);
        }

        if ('127.0.0.1' !== $request->getClientIp()) {
            return new Response(
                'Invalid HTTP method',
                Response::HTTP_BAD_REQUEST
            );
        }

        $response = new Response();
        if ($this->getStore()->purge($request->getUri())) {
            $response->setStatusCode(Response::HTTP_OK, 'Purged');
        } else {
            $response->setStatusCode(Response::HTTP_NOT_FOUND, 'Not found');
        }

        return $response;
    }
}

Caution

You must protect the PURGE HTTP method somehow to avoid random people purging your cached data.

Purge instructs the cache to drop a resource in all its variants (according to the Vary header, see Varying the Response for HTTP Cache). An alternative to purging is refreshing a content. Refreshing means that the caching proxy is instructed to discard its local cache and fetch the content again. This way, the new content is already available in the cache. The drawback of refreshing is that variants are not invalidated.

In many applications, the same content bit is used on various pages with different URLs. More flexible concepts exist for those cases:

Banning invalidates responses matching regular expressions on the URL or other criteria;

Cache tagging lets you add a tag for each content used in a response so that you can invalidate all URLs containing a certain content.

Varying the Response for HTTP Cache

So far, it’s been assumed that each URI has exactly one representation of the target resource. By default, HTTP caching is done by using the URI of the resource as the cache key. If two people request the same URI of a cacheable resource, the second person will receive the cached version.

Sometimes this isn’t enough and different versions of the same URI need to be cached based on one or more request header values. For instance, if you compress pages when the client supports it, any given URI has two representations: one when the client supports compression, and one when it does not. This determination is done by the value of the Accept-Encoding request header.

In this case, you need the cache to store both a compressed and uncompressed version of the response for the particular URI and return them based on the request’s Accept-Encoding value. This is done by using the Vary response header, which is a comma-separated list of different headers whose values trigger a different representation of the requested resource:

1

|

Vary: Accept-Encoding, User-Agent

Tip

This particular Vary header would cache different versions of each resource based on the URI and the value of the Accept-Encoding and User-Agent request header.

The Response object offers a clean interface for managing the Vary header:

// sets one vary header
$response->setVary('Accept-Encoding');

// sets multiple vary headers
$response->setVary(['Accept-Encoding', 'User-Agent']);

The setVary() method takes a header name or an array of header names for which the response varies.

Working with Edge Side Includes

Gateway caches are a great way to make your website perform better. But they have one limitation: they can only cache whole pages. If your pages contain dynamic sections, such as the user name or a shopping cart, you are out of luck. Fortunately, Symfony provides a solution for these cases, based on a technology called ESI [http://www.w3.org/TR/esi-lang], or Edge Side Includes. Akamai wrote this specification in 2001 and it allows specific parts of a page to have a different caching strategy than the main page.

The ESI specification describes tags you can embed in your pages to communicate with the gateway cache. Only one tag is implemented in Symfony, include, as this is the only useful one outside of Akamai context:

 1
 2
 3
 4
 5
 6
 7
 8
 9
10
11

|

<!DOCTYPE html>
<html>
    <body>
        <!-- ... some content -->

        <!-- Embed the content of another page here -->
        <esi:include src="http://..."/>

        <!-- ... more content -->
    </body>
</html>

Note

Notice from the example that each ESI tag requires a fully-qualified URL. An ESI tag represents a page fragment that can be fetched via the given URL.

When a request is handled, the gateway cache fetches the entire page from its cache or requests it from the backend application. If the response contains one or more ESI tags, these are processed in the same way. In other words, the gateway cache either retrieves the included page fragment from its cache or requests the page fragment from the backend application again. When all the ESI tags have been resolved, the gateway cache merges each into the main page and sends the final content to the client.

All of this happens transparently at the gateway cache level (i.e. outside of your application). As you’ll see, if you choose to take advantage of ESI tags, Symfony makes the process of including them almost effortless.

Using ESI in Symfony

First, to use ESI, be sure to enable it in your application configuration:

YAML

1
2
3
4

|

# config/packages/framework.yaml
framework:
    # ...
    esi: { enabled: true }

XML

 1
 2
 3
 4
 5
 6
 7
 8
 9
10
11
12
13
14
15

|

<!-- config/packages/framework.xml -->
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<container xmlns="http://symfony.com/schema/dic/services"
    xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
    xmlns:framework="http://symfony.com/schema/dic/symfony"
    xsi:schemaLocation="http://symfony.com/schema/dic/services
        https://symfony.com/schema/dic/services/services-1.0.xsd
        http://symfony.com/schema/dic/symfony
        https://symfony.com/schema/dic/symfony/symfony-1.0.xsd">

    <framework:config>
        <!-- ... -->
        <framework:esi enabled="true"/>
    </framework:config>
</container>

PHP

1
2
3
4
5

|

// config/packages/framework.php
$container->loadFromExtension('framework', [
    // ...
    'esi' => ['enabled' => true],
]);

Now, suppose you have a page that is relatively static, except for a news ticker at the bottom of the content. With ESI, you can cache the news ticker independently of the rest of the page:

// src/Controller/DefaultController.php
namespace App\Controller;

// ...
class DefaultController extends AbstractController
{
    public function about()
    {
        $response = $this->render('static/about.html.twig');
        $response->setPublic();
        $response->setMaxAge(600);

        return $response;
    }
}

In this example, the response is marked as public to make the full page cacheable for all requests with a lifetime of ten minutes. Next, include the news ticker in the template by embedding an action. This is done via the render() helper (for more details, see how to embed controllers in templates).

As the embedded content comes from another page (or controller for that matter), Symfony uses the standard render helper to configure ESI tags:

1
2
3
4
5
6
7

|

{# templates/static/about.html.twig #}

{# you can use a controller reference #}
{{ render_esi(controller('App\\Controller\\NewsController::latest', { 'maxPerPage': 5 })) }}

{# ... or a URL #}
{{ render_esi(url('latest_news', { 'maxPerPage': 5 })) }}

By using the esi renderer (via the render_esi() Twig function), you tell Symfony that the action should be rendered as an ESI tag. You might be wondering why you would want to use a helper instead of just writing the ESI tag yourself. That’s because using a helper makes your application work even if there is no gateway cache installed.

Tip

As you’ll see below, the maxPerPage variable you pass is available as an argument to your controller (i.e. $maxPerPage). The variables passed through render_esi also become part of the cache key so that you have unique caches for each combination of variables and values.

When using the default render() function (or setting the renderer to inline), Symfony merges the included page content into the main one before sending the response to the client. But if you use the esi renderer (i.e. call render_esi()) and if Symfony detects that it’s talking to a gateway cache that supports ESI, it generates an ESI include tag. But if there is no gateway cache or if it does not support ESI, Symfony will just merge the included page content within the main one as it would have done if you had used render().

Note

Symfony detects if a gateway cache supports ESI via another Akamai specification that is supported out of the box by the Symfony reverse proxy.

The embedded action can now specify its own caching rules entirely independently of the master page:

// src/Controller/NewsController.php
namespace App\Controller;

// ...
class NewsController extends AbstractController
{
    public function latest($maxPerPage)
    {
        // ...
        $response->setPublic();
        $response->setMaxAge(60);

        return $response;
    }
}

In this example, the embedded action is cached publicly too because the contents are the same for all requests. However, in other cases you may need to make this response non-public and even non-cacheable, depending on your needs.

Putting all the above code together, with ESI the full page cache will be valid for 600 seconds, but the news component cache will only last for 60 seconds.

When using a controller reference, the ESI tag should reference the embedded action as an accessible URL so the gateway cache can fetch it independently of the rest of the page. Symfony takes care of generating a unique URL for any controller reference and it is able to route them properly thanks to the FragmentListener [https://github.com/symfony/symfony/blob/master/src/Symfony/Component/HttpKernel/EventListener/FragmentListener.php] that must be enabled in your configuration:

YAML

1
2
3
4

|

# config/packages/framework.yaml
framework:
    # ...
    fragments: { path: /_fragment }

XML

 1
 2
 3
 4
 5
 6
 7
 8
 9
10
11
12
13
14
15

|

<!-- config/packages/framework.xml -->
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<container xmlns="http://symfony.com/schema/dic/services"
    xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
    xmlns:framework="http://symfony.com/schema/dic/symfony"
    xsi:schemaLocation="http://symfony.com/schema/dic/services
        https://symfony.com/schema/dic/services/services-1.0.xsd
        http://symfony.com/schema/dic/symfony
        https://symfony.com/schema/dic/symfony/symfony-1.0.xsd">

    <!-- ... -->
    <framework:config>
        <framework:fragment path="/_fragment"/>
    </framework:config>
</container>

PHP

1
2
3
4
5

|

// config/packages/framework.php
$container->loadFromExtension('framework', [
    // ...
    'fragments' => ['path' => '/_fragment'],
]);

One great advantage of the ESI renderer is that you can make your application as dynamic as needed and at the same time, hit the application as little as possible.

Caution

The fragment listener only responds to signed requests. Requests are only signed when using the fragment renderer and the render_esi Twig function.

The render_esi helper supports two other useful options:

alt

Used as the alt attribute on the ESI tag, which allows you to specify an alternative URL to be used if the src cannot be found.

ignore_errors

If set to true, an onerror attribute will be added to the ESI with a value of continue indicating that, in the event of a failure, the gateway cache will remove the ESI tag silently.

HTTP Cache Validation

When a resource needs to be updated as soon as a change is made to the underlying data, the expiration model falls short. With the expiration model [https://tools.ietf.org/html/rfc2616#section-13.2], the application won’t be asked to return the updated response until the cache finally becomes stale.

The validation model addresses this issue. Under this model, the cache continues to store responses. The difference is that, for each request, the cache asks the application if the cached response is still valid or if it needs to be regenerated. If the cache is still valid, your application should return a 304 status code and no content. This tells the cache that it’s OK to return the cached response.

Under this model, you only save CPU if you’re able to determine that the cached response is still valid by doing less work than generating the whole page again (see below for an implementation example).

Tip

The 304 status code means “Not Modified”. It’s important because with this status code the response does not contain the actual content being requested. Instead, the response only consists of the response headers that tells the cache that it can use its stored version of the content.

Like with expiration, there are two different HTTP headers that can be used to implement the validation model: ETag and Last-Modified.

Expiration and Validation

You can use both validation and expiration within the same Response. As expiration wins over validation, you can benefit from the best of both worlds. In other words, by using both expiration and validation, you can instruct the cache to serve the cached content, while checking back at some interval (the expiration) to verify that the content is still valid.

Tip

You can also define HTTP caching headers for expiration and validation by using annotations. See the FrameworkExtraBundle documentation [https://symfony.com/doc/current/bundles/SensioFrameworkExtraBundle/annotations/cache.html].

Validation with the ETag Header

The HTTP ETag [https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/HTTP_ETag] (“entity-tag”) header is an optional HTTP header whose value is an arbitrary string that uniquely identifies one representation of the target resource. It’s entirely generated and set by your application so that you can tell, for example, if the /about resource that’s stored by the cache is up-to-date with what your application would return.

An ETag is like a fingerprint and is used to quickly compare if two different versions of a resource are equivalent. Like fingerprints, each ETag must be unique across all representations of the same resource.

To see a short implementation, generate the ETag as the md5 of the content:

// src/Controller/DefaultController.php
namespace App\Controller;

use Symfony\Bundle\FrameworkBundle\Controller\AbstractController;
use Symfony\Component\HttpFoundation\Request;

class DefaultController extends AbstractController
{
    public function homepage(Request $request)
    {
        $response = $this->render('static/homepage.html.twig');
        $response->setEtag(md5($response->getContent()));
        $response->setPublic(); // make sure the response is public/cacheable
        $response->isNotModified($request);

        return $response;
    }
}

The isNotModified() [https://github.com/symfony/symfony/blob/master/src/Symfony/Component/HttpFoundation/Response.php] method compares the If-None-Match header with the ETag response header. If the two match, the method automatically sets the Response status code to 304.

Note

When using mod_deflate or mod_brotli in Apache 2.4, the original ETag value is modified (e.g. if ETag was foo, Apache turns it into foo-gzip or foo-br), which breaks the ETag-based validation.

You can control this behavior with the DeflateAlterETag [https://httpd.apache.org/docs/trunk/mod/mod_deflate.html#deflatealteretag] and BrotliAlterETag [https://httpd.apache.org/docs/2.4/mod/mod_brotli.html#brotlialteretag] directives. Alternatively, you can use the following Apache configuration to keep both the original ETag and the modified one when compressing responses:

1

|

RequestHeader edit "If-None-Match" '^"((.*)-(gzip|br))"$' '"$1", "$2"'

Note

The cache sets the If-None-Match header on the request to the ETag of the original cached response before sending the request back to the app. This is how the cache and server communicate with each other and decide whether or not the resource has been updated since it was cached.

This algorithm works and is very generic, but you need to create the whole Response before being able to compute the ETag, which is sub-optimal. In other words, it saves on bandwidth, but not CPU cycles.

In the Optimizing your Code with Validation section, you’ll see how validation can be used more intelligently to determine the validity of a cache without doing so much work.

Tip

Symfony also supports weak ETag``s by passing ``true as the second argument to the setEtag() [https://github.com/symfony/symfony/blob/master/src/Symfony/Component/HttpFoundation/Response.php] method.

Validation with the Last-Modified Header

The Last-Modified header is the second form of validation. According to the HTTP specification, “The Last-Modified header field indicates the date and time at which the origin server believes the representation was last modified.” In other words, the application decides whether or not the cached content has been updated based on whether or not it’s been updated since the response was cached.

For instance, you can use the latest update date for all the objects needed to compute the resource representation as the value for the Last-Modified header value:

// src/Controller/ArticleController.php
namespace App\Controller;

// ...
use App\Entity\Article;
use Symfony\Component\HttpFoundation\Request;
use Symfony\Component\HttpFoundation\Response;

class ArticleController extends AbstractController
{
    public function show(Article $article, Request $request)
    {
        $author = $article->getAuthor();

        $articleDate = new \DateTime($article->getUpdatedAt());
        $authorDate = new \DateTime($author->getUpdatedAt());

        $date = $authorDate > $articleDate ? $authorDate : $articleDate;

        $response = new Response();
        $response->setLastModified($date);
        // Set response as public. Otherwise it will be private by default.
        $response->setPublic();

        if ($response->isNotModified($request)) {
            return $response;
        }

        // ... do more work to populate the response with the full content

        return $response;
    }
}

The isNotModified() [https://github.com/symfony/symfony/blob/master/src/Symfony/Component/HttpFoundation/Response.php] method compares the If-Modified-Since header with the Last-Modified response header. If they are equivalent, the Response will be set to a 304 status code.

Note

The cache sets the If-Modified-Since header on the request to the Last-Modified of the original cached response before sending the request back to the app. This is how the cache and server communicate with each other and decide whether or not the resource has been updated since it was cached.

Optimizing your Code with Validation

The main goal of any caching strategy is to lighten the load on the application. Put another way, the less you do in your application to return a 304 response, the better. The Response::isNotModified() method does exactly that:

// src/Controller/ArticleController.php
namespace App\Controller;

// ...
use Symfony\Component\HttpFoundation\Request;
use Symfony\Component\HttpFoundation\Response;

class ArticleController extends AbstractController
{
    public function show($articleSlug, Request $request)
    {
        // Get the minimum information to compute
        // the ETag or the Last-Modified value
        // (based on the Request, data is retrieved from
        // a database or a key-value store for instance)
        $article = ...;

        // create a Response with an ETag and/or a Last-Modified header
        $response = new Response();
        $response->setEtag($article->computeETag());
        $response->setLastModified($article->getPublishedAt());

        // Set response as public. Otherwise it will be private by default.
        $response->setPublic();

        // Check that the Response is not modified for the given Request
        if ($response->isNotModified($request)) {
            // return the 304 Response immediately
            return $response;
        }

        // do more work here - like retrieving more data
        $comments = ...;

        // or render a template with the $response you've already started
        return $this->render('article/show.html.twig', [
            'article' => $article,
            'comments' => $comments,
        ], $response);
    }
}

When the Response is not modified, the isNotModified() automatically sets the response status code to 304, removes the content, and removes some headers that must not be present for 304 responses (see setNotModified() [https://github.com/symfony/symfony/blob/master/src/Symfony/Component/HttpFoundation/Response.php]).